Ed Lee Gossett Papers, Inclusive: 1935-1953, Bulk: 1945-1951.
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
- Palestine, 1934-1951; 6
  - United Nations Partition, 1947-1948; 4
    This subseries contains speeches before the UN Ad Hoc Committee on the Palestine Question in October 1947. Furthermore, it includes reports from that committee to the UN General Assembly, speeches before the assembly, and a record of the Assembly’s proceedings in November 1947. Finally, it holds newspaper articles and editorials about the partitioning of Palestine by the United Nations.
    - General, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - General, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - UN Documents, Ad Hoc Committee, 1947 October (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - UN Documents, Ad Hoc Committee, 1947 October (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - UN Documents, General Assembly, 1947 November (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - UN Documents, General Assembly, 1947 November (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Race Relations, 1934-1951; 7
  This series includes books, pamphlets, open letters, circulars, and periodicals illustrating some American reactions to Jews. They include publications espousing bigotry against Jews and some by Christian organizations, particularly issues of The Cross and the Flag. Publications from 1942 to 1950 describe Judaism, and the series also contains speeches before Congress on the visible effects of racial prejudice. Finally, it includes private reports to an unknown recipient on activities of Jewish communities in California from 1948 to 1949.
  - General, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Anti-Jewish Tracts/Pamphlets, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Anti-Jewish Tracts/Pamphlets, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Anti-Jewish Tracts/Pamphlets, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Christian Publications against Jews, 1947-1949 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Christian Publications against Jews, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Christian Publications against Jews, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Publications on Judaism, 1942-1950 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Reports, 1943-1950 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Tidelands, 1933-1953; 8
  This series contains publications, correspondence, bills, hearings, legal filings, and speeches relating to the Texas tidelands controversy. Speeches, publications, and memorandums on the validity of federal control over tidelands are located in the "General" subseries, while bills, case filings, committee hearings, and correspondence each have their own subseries.
  - General, 1933-1951; 1
    These materials include press releases announcing bills introduced by various Congressmen to resolve the tidelands controversy, and speeches by Gossett before the House and at other events, as well as speeches and remarks by others before Congress. The subseries also contains long memorandums from the Texas State Teacher’s Association and Price Daniel, Texas Attorney General, claiming rightful state ownership in the tidelands controversy. Likewise, it includes resolutions by state legislatures and other organizations supporting the states’ position in the controversy. Some resolutions of organizations with cover letters still attached are located in the Tideland/Correspondence subseries. Publications include booklets, periodicals, and newsletters about the tidelands controversy, as well as legal commentaries on the issue.
    - General, 1933-1951 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Memos, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Press Releases, 1948-1951 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Publications, 1948-1950 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Publications, 1950-1951 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Publications, Legal Commentaries, 1948-1950 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Resolutions, 1948-1951 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Speeches, 1947-1951 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Clippings, 1947-1949 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Clippings, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Resolutions, 1945-1953; 2
    This subseries covers materials pertaining to legislation in the Tidelands Controversy. It contains copies of bills introduced by Gossett to secure Congressional approval for state ownership of disputed tidelands. Drafts containing similar language to introduced bills but having no dates have been kept separate from the officially published resolutions. The subseries also includes memos on the different bills, and reports from the House Judiciary Committee on bills, including drafts of these reports.
    - Bills, 1945-June 1949 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Bills, 1949-1953 August (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Untitled Drafts, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Memos on Legislation, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Memos on Legislation, 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Memos on Legislation, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Reports on Bills, 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Cases, 1947-1950; 3
    These materials pertain to three Supreme Court cases over state ownership of tidelands. They include letters between Price Daniel, Attorney General of Texas, and Gossett about Daniel’s activities in US v State of Texas. Also included are a few filings with the Supreme Court in cases involving California and Louisiana, as well as a larger number of filings for the case involving Texas. Finally, the subseries contains publications reacting to the Supreme Court’s ruling in the Texas case.
    - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - US v. State of California, Briefs, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - US v. State of Louisiana, Briefs, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - US v. State of Texas, Briefs, 1948-1949 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - US v. State of Texas, Briefs, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - US v. State of Texas, Briefs, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - US v. State of Texas, Briefs, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - US v. State of Texas, Publications, 1947-1949 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - US v. State of Texas, Publications, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Committee Hearings, 1949-1951; 4
    This subseries contains statements and reports by lawyers, engineers, and members of the oil industry for the House and Senate Judiciary Committees on legislation over the tidelands controversy. The bulk of the materials comprise the House Judiciary Committee’s hearings in August 1949 on HR 5991 and 5992, bills introduced by Gossett to secure the rights of states to the tidelands. The materials also include statements for the House committee, and for the Senate Judiciary Committee.
    - House Committee Hearings on HR 5991 and 5992 (1 of 3), 1949 August (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - House Committee Hearings on HR 5991 and 5992 (2 of 3), 1949 August (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - House Committee Hearings on HR 5991 and 5992 (3 of 3), 1949 August (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - House Committee Hearings, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Senate Committee Hearings, 1950-1951 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1951; 5
    These letters primarily consist of correspondence between Gossett, Price Daniel, Texas Attorney General, and Robert Lee Bobbitt, Chairman of the Texas Bar Association’s Tidelands Committee, but also contain letters from other Texas state officials, citizens, and organizations voicing concern over the tidelands conflict. The substance of this correspondence portrays the concurrent efforts of Gossett in committee and Daniel in United States v. State of Texas to oppose federal seizure of tidelands.
    - Letters, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Letters, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Letters, 1949 January-April (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Letters, 1949 May-December (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Letters, 1950 January-May (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Letters, 1950 June (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Letters, 1950 July-August (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Letters, 1950 September-December (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Letters, 1951 January (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1951 March (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1951 April-May (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1951 June (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1951 July (Box 17, Folder 5)